TED:时光穿梭有可能吗？
Is time travel possible
Have you ever daydreamed
你曾白日梦过
about traveling through time,
穿越时空吗？
perhaps fast forward in the centuries
或者穿越到几百年之后
and see the distant future?
及看到遥远未来？
Well, time travel is possible,
让我告诉你，穿越时空是有可能的。
and what's more,
而且，还有的是
it's already been done.
它已经被实现了。
Meet Sergei Krikalev,
谢尔盖.克里卡列夫
the greatest time traveler in human history.
是人类历史上最伟大的穿越时空者。
This Russian cosmonaut holds the record
这位俄罗斯宇航员创了记录。
for the most amount of time
他是环绕地球
spent orbiting our planet,
时间最久的人，
a total of 803 days, 9 hours, and 39 minutes.
总共803天9小时39分钟。
During his stay in space,
当他在太空的时候，
he time traveled into his own future
他时空穿越到自己的未来，
by 0.02 seconds.
且用了0.02秒。
Traveling at 17,500 miles an hour,
当时，他在太空时的行驶速度为每小时17500英里。
he experienced an effect
他体验了一种
known as time dilation,
名为"时间膨胀"的效应。
and one day the same effect
而且，終一天 这种效应
might make significant time travel
将会让穿越时空之时间更持久
to the future commonplace.
也变以家常便饭的事。
To see why moving faster through space
如果想了解为什么加快在空间里的行驶速度
affects passage of time,
会影响时间流逝的速度,
we need to go back to the 1880s,
我们得回到1880年,
when two American scientists,
当时 两个美国科学家
Albert Michelson and Edward Morley,
阿尔伯特?迈克尔逊 和 爱德华?莫雷
were trying to measure the effect
尝试衡量
of the Earth's movement around the Sun
地球绕太阳
on the speed of light.
对光速有什么影响。
When a beam of light was moving
他们以为， 当一束光
in the same direction as the Earth,
和地球往同一个方向移动时,
they expected the light to travel faster.
光的速度会更快。
And when the Earth was moving in the opposite direction,
而且，当地球与光束作反方向移动时，
they expected it to go slower.
光的速度会减慢。
But they found something very curious.
但是结果并非如此，有趣的是
The speed of light remained the same
不管地球往哪个方向移动
no matter what the Earth was doing.
光的速度并没有改变。
Two decades later, Albert Einstein was thinking
20年之后，爱因斯坦回到
about the consequences
这个问题的結果上：
of that never-changing speed of light.
光速不变。
And it was his conclusions,
他的结论是：
formulated in the theory of special relativity,
他所創的“相对论”
that opened the door
开启了
into the world of time travel.
穿越时空的大门。
Imagine a man named Jack,
试想 一個名為杰克的人
standing in the middle of a train carriage,
站在一辆火车卡中間
traveling at a steady speed.
在稳定状态下移动，
Jack's bored
杰克覺无聊
and starts bouncing a ball up and down.
开始在地上上下拍球
What would Jill, standing on the platform,
這个时候站在月台上的吉尔
see through the window
会透过窗口所看到
as the train whistles through.
是什么？
Well, between Jack dropping the ball
在杰克扔下球
and catching it again,
和接著球之间
Jill would have seen him move
吉尔会看到杰克
slightly further down the track,
和火车一起向前移动，
resulting in her seeing the ball
結果她看到的球
follow a triangular path.
是以三角形的路线移动的。
This means Jill sees the ball
意思是，吉尔看到的球
travel further than Jack does
比杰克所看到的 移动得更远
in the same time period.
在同一个时间段里。
And because speed is distance divided by time,
因为速度等于距离除以时间，
Jill actually sees the ball move faster.
事實上 吉尔所看到球比杰克所看到的移动得更快。
But what if Jack's bouncing ball
但是，如果我们把杰克的球
is replaced with two mirrors
用两面镜子作代替
which bounce a beam of light between them?
而在镜子之间有一束光來回反弹。
Jack still sees the beam dropping down
杰克依然会看到光束反弹
and Jill still sees the light beam
吉尔还是会看到该光束
travel a longer distance,
移动得更远，
except this time Jack and Jill
例外的是，这次杰克和吉尔
cannot disagree on the speed
却会对光的速度有分歧。
because the speed of light
這是因为光的速度
remains the same no matter what.
无论如何 還是 保留不变。
And if the speed is the same
如果速度是一样的话，
while the distance is different,
而距离却不一样，
this means the time taken will be different as well.
那花的时间将也不一样。
Thus, time must tick at different rates
所以 当人们对他人相对地移动时，
for people moving relative to each other.
时间一定以不一样的速率流逝。
Imagine that Jack and Jill have highly accurate watches
试想如果杰克和吉尔都有非常精确的手表。
that they synchronize before Jack boarded the train.
他们在杰克上火车前校对好时间。
During the experiment, Jack and Jill would each see
当这个实验中，杰克和吉尔会看到
their own watch ticking normally.
自己的手表正常的走。
But if they meet up again later
但是如果他们在实验结束后相遇
to compare watches,
比对彼此手表时，
less time would have elapsed on Jack's watch,
他们会发现杰克的手表会走慢一些，
balancing the fact
因此解释了这事实：
that Jill saw the light move further.
吉尔看到的光移动得更远。
This idea may sound crazy,
这听上去很诡异，
but like any good scientific theory,
但是，像任何一个完好的科学理论，
it can be tested.
它是可以被测试的。
In the 1970s, scientists boarded a plane
在1970年左右，
with some super accurate atomic clocks
科学家们 校对了一些超级准确的原子钟
that were synchronized
一起带到飞机上去，
with some others left on the ground.
而数个原子钟则留在陆地上，
After the plane had flown around the world,
当飞机环球飞行之后，
the clocks on board showed a different time
他们发现飞机上的原子钟
from those left behind.
和地球上的原子钟上显示的时间是不一样的。
Of course, at the speed of trains and planes,
当然，以火车与飞机的速度，
the effect is minuscule.
对时间膨胀的影响是很微小的。
But the faster you go,
但是行驶的速度越快，
the more time dilates.
时间的膨胀越多。
For astronauts orbiting the Earth for 800 days,
如果宇航员们环绕地球800天，
it starts to add up.
其影响就会明显。
But what affects humans also affects machines.
言而，影响人类的也会影响机器。
Satellites of the global positioning system
GPS的卫星
are also hurdling around the Earth
同時也环绕著地球行驶，
at thousands of miles an hour.
且速度为每小时数千英里。
So, time dilation kicks in here, too.
因此，时间在这情況也显见膨胀的。
In fact, their speed causes
事實上，GPS卫星的行驶速度导致
the atomic clocks on board
飞行著的原子钟
to disagree with clocks on the ground
与地上的原子钟之間
by seven millionths of a second daily.
产生每天7百万分之一秒之差。
Left uncorrected,
如果再不做校对的话，
this would cause GPS to lose accuracy
这将会令GPS失去准确性
by a few kilometers each day.
且产生每天几公里差異 。
So, what does all this have to do with time travel
那么，这些和穿越时空
to the far, distant future?
和去遥远的未来有什么关系呢？
Well, the faster you go,
当行驶的速度越快，
the greater the effect of time dilation.
时间膨胀的效应越大。
If you could travel really close
如果你行驶的速度真的能夠接近
to the speed of light, say 99.9999%,
光速的話，比方说，百分之99.9999,
on a round-trip through space
绕太空來回一圈，
for what seemed to you like ten years,
对你来说可能像过了10年，
you'd actually return to Earth
但是当你回到地球时，
around the year 9000.
将会是9000那年左右。
Who knows what you'd see when you returned?!?
到那时候，谁知道你回来后会看到什么？
Humanity merged with machines,
人类与机器分不开，
extinct due to climate change
灭绝原於全球暖化
or asteroid impact,
或行星之間撞击，
or inhabiting a permanent colony on Mars.
又或是人类在火星定居了。
But the trouble is,
但问题是，
getting heavy things like people,
要把像人一样那么重的东西，
not to mention space ships,
莫说太空飞船了，
up to such speeds requires
移动到达接近光速般，
unimaginable amounts of energy.
是需要不能想象的巨大能量。
It already takes enormous particle accelerators
龐大量的粒子加速器
like the Large Hadron Collider
如大型粒子对撞机
to accelerate tiny subatomic particles
已被需要来把微小的亚原子粒子加速
to close to light speed.
到达接近光速了。
But one day, if we can develop the tools
但是终有一天，如果我们能够发明一些工具
to accelerate ourselves to similar speeds,
可以让我们加速到如光速度般，
then we may regularly send time travelers
到那时候，我们可能隨時可以把穿越时空者
into the future,
送到遥远的未来，
bringing with them tales of a long, forgotten past.
还有带著我们 古老，被遺忘的故事去。